Preliminary Guide to the Kiev Foundation graphics arts and artifacts collection, 1493-1969 K0005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Jewish art, 1910-1948; K0005 Series 1; 2 Linear Feet; 1 Linear feet (Box 14, Box 15, Box 1, Box 3)
  - Chess in Art, 1976 (Map-folder 32)
    Poster, Goldman's Art Gallery, Haifa, 1976; 21 5/8" x 33 1/16"
  - A Jewish Woman with her Veil and Rich Ornaments, 1732 (Map-folder 43)
    Copper plate engraving taken from the first English-language edition of Augustin Calmet's Dictionnaire historique, critique, chronologique, géographique et littéral de la Bible, originally published in Paris (1722). Subsequent English-language editions contained a different set of plates. This engraving was meant to accompany the entry for "Veil".
    Augustin Calmet. An historical, critical, geographical, chronological, and etymological dictionary of the Holy Bible, in three volumes. Samuel D'Oyly and John Colson, translators. London: Printed for J.J. and P. Knapton, D. Midwinter and A. Ward, A. Bettesworth and C. Hitch, J. Pemberton, J. Osborn and T. Longman, C. Rivington, F. Clay [and 3 others in London], 1732.
    9" x 15 1/2"
  - A Jewish Woman Going to the Synagogue, 1732 (Map-folder 44)
    Copper plate engraving taken from the first English-language edition of Augustin Calmet's Dictionnaire historique, critique, chronologique, géographique et littéral de la Bible, originally published in Paris (1722). Subsequent English-language editions contained a different set of plates.
  - Tephilims or Philacteries of the Jews, 1732 (Map-folder 45)
  - A Jew with the Mezuzoth in his Hand, 1732 (Map-folder 46)
    9 1/4" x 15 1/2"
  - The Court Consisting of XXIII Judges according to the Rabbins, 1732 (Map-folder 47)
    9 3/8" x 15 1/2"
  - Le Sanhédrin Ou Grand Conseil Des Juifs, c. 1722-1783 (Map-folder 48)
    (c. 1722-1783) Copper plate engraving taken from Augustin Calmet's Dictionnaire historique, critique, chronologique, géographique et littéral de la Bible, originally published in Paris (1722).
    9 1/2" x 15 1/4"
  - Figures des Instruments de Musique dont il est parlé dans l'Ecriture, c. 1722-1783 (Map-folder 49)
    9 7/8" x 15 1/4"
  - Two leaves from an early English Bible, c. 17th century (Map-folder 50)
    Leaves are taken from Deuteronomy; 11" x 16"
  - Leaf from an early English Bible, c. 17th century (Map-folder 51)
    This leaf, which appears to have originated from a different edition than the two Deuteronomy leaves in this collection, includes "The Prayer of Menasseh King of the Iewes" and "A Very Profitable Declaration for the Understanding of the Histories of Ezra, Nehemiah, Ester, Daniel, and Diverse Other Places of Scripture". 10 3/4" x 15 3/4"
  - Map of Asia Minor Showing the Land and Rivers of Eden and Illustrating the First Division of the Earth among the Sons of Noah, c. 1860 (Map-folder 52)
    Leaf taken from Biblical Natural Science: Being the Explanation of all References in Holy Scripture to Geology, Botany, Zoology, and Physical Geography by John Duns (London: William MacKenzie, [186-?]); 12 1/2" x 9 1/4"
  - Map of the Journeyings of the Israelites from Egypt to Canaan (Map-folder 53)
  - Map of Palestine in the Time of Christ (Map-folder 54)
  - A New Map of Palestine or the Holy Land, c. 1872 (Map-folder 55)
    From Mitchell's New General Atlas, Philadelphia: S. Augustus Mitchell, 1872.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Diane Stamm, April 18, 2013
  - Pair of undated color prints bound together: "Die Haupt-Synagoge in Fürth erbaut im Jahre 1616", engraved by G. Löwensohn (1839); and "Synagoge, Innenraum" (Map-folder 56)
    Prints are adhered to matting boards enclosed within hard cloth-bound covers. The closed book measures 16" x 14.25" x 0.25"
  - Genealogica Herodum, engraving by Jan Goeree (1670-1731), 1714 (Map-folder 57)
    Engraving published as a fold-out plate in Adriaan Reelant. Hadriani Relandi Palaestina ex monumentis veteribus illustrata. Trajecti Batavorum: Ex libraria Guilielmi Broedelet, 1714. 17 1/2" x 7 3/4".
  - Jérusalem et ses environs (postcard set), ca. 1900 (Box 15, Folder 136)
    Gift of Patricia Miller 2016 July 07 (Accession 2016.108)
    General
    Behar et Fils, publishers. Set of 12 postcards. 3.5" x 5.5" x 0.25".
- Antisemitica, 1493-1969; K0005 Series 2; 5 Linear feet (Box 12, Box 11, Box 13, Box 2, Box 10)
  This series contains posters, woodcuts, a Yellow Star of David Badge, and cards ranging from 1493 to 1969 with the bulk of materials dating from about 1900 to 1950. Topically, they chronicle anti-Semitism from various periods of heightened persecution such as the Inquisition and Nazi Germany.
  - Knock and ye shall enter, c. 1828- c. 1830 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Hand-colored etching by William Heath. Published by T. McLean, London. An old clothes dealer and a Moroccan Jewish peddler at the door of the House of Commons.
  - Jews at luncheon (or/ A peep into Dukes place), 1794 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Hand-colored etching by Thomas Rowlandson.
  - King Jerry treating his Jewish subjects with Westphalia Venison, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Hand-colored etching. Published by Thomas Tegg. Print made by Charles Williams after George Moutard Woodward, London. Satire on the emancipation of the Jews of Westphalia by King Jerome. Also refers to supposed Jewish support of Napoleon.
  - Humours of Houndsditch (or/ Mrs. Shevi in a longing condition), 1813 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Etching by Thomas Rowlandson. Published by Thomas Tegg, London. A Jew brings home a suckling pig.
  - A Jew and a bishop, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Hand-colored etching by Isaac Cruikshank from an original by Woodward. Published by Allen & West, London. Scene in the Pump Room at Bath from Macklin's comedy 'The Man of the World'.
  - Original fifteenth century woodcut, 1493 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    Leaf from Hartmann Schedel's, "Weltchronik," or, "Chronicle of the World," better known today as the "Nuremberg Chronicle", depicting the burning of the Jew Eleazar and his family.
  - Original fifteenth century woodcut, 1493 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    Leaf from Hartmann Schedel's, "Weltchronik," or, "Chronicle of the World," better known today as the "Nuremberg Chronicle", depicting a ritual bloodletting.
  - Finance in the USA is 98% in Jewish hands, 1939-1942 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Shows Secretary of U.S. Treasury Henry Morgenthau.
  - The media in the USA in 97% controlled by Jewish hands, 1939-1945 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Shows a younger Adolph Ochs, editor of the New York Times.
  - Et derriere: Le Juif, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Depicting crudely stereotyped Jew lurking behind the flags of the principal Allied Powers.
  - Red Army soldier, Are you going to liberate other nations? First liberate yourself from your oppressors!, 1941 ca. (Box 7, Folder 40)
    An anti-Semitic poster with Russian text and caricatures. German issued propaganda encouraging the common soldier to rise up against the NKVD (Stalin's secret police), Stalin and ultimately the Jews.
  - Antisemitic poster from Argentina, 1930 ca. (Box 8, Folder 95)
    Probably produced between 1930 and 1945. Produced by a medical student organization and probably aimed primarily at other students, the poster appears to be an attempt to draw on fears of Christian students in the medical fields that Jews were making inroads that would threaten the virtual monopoly on these fields by Christians. The PIF! of course, is the sound of an insecticide sprayer (note the "I" in PIF has a nozzle which is spraying poison on ;the Jewish caricatures). The phenomenon of Argentinean anti-Semitism is especially interesting, since Argentina itself was a Mecca for both Jewish settlement form the 1890s through the 1950s, as well as a haven for Nazis and proto-Nazis during the same period.
  - Wings of the carrion crow, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    Housed with University Archive material in the first map case in FF1.
  - Scrapbook of Polish anti-Semitic cartoons, 1900 ca. (Box 10, Folder 99)
    Accompanied by translations and photocopies of the original images.
  - Thirty-three antisemitic cartoons from "Puck" and "Harper's Weekly" periodicals, 1870 ca. (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Nazi Flag, undated (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - Italian Fascist Flag, undated (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - Book of Graphics from Nazi Germany, undated (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - Prerov- Nadrazi, 1906 (Box 13, Folder 104)
  - My Business is Picking Up, undated (Box 13, Folder 105)
  - Jen Drazme Se Povzdy Ceskeho Naroda, 1905-1925 (Box 13, Folder 106)
  - At Zije Republika, 1905-1925 (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - I Am Doing Rushing (Russian) Business, undated (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - I'm Passing the Time, undated (Box 13, Folder 109)
  - Vy Not?, undated (Box 13, Folder 110)
  - Such A Business, undated (Box 13, Folder 111)
  - Der Mandelbaum Und Seine Fruchte, 1900-1930 (Box 13, Folder 112)
  - Our Flag, 1906 ca. (Box 13, Folder 113)
    The Jew holds a flag which satirizes and stereotypes the Jewish people. Elements include: the three balls of the pawn shop; old clothing (for tailoring), "Our Friend", the building fire; "Our Enemy", the fireman; et al.
  - Russian Jews Caricatures of Three Jewish Women, 1928 ca. (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - The Little Cohen "Haven't You Seen The Little Cohen?", 1920 ca. (Box 13, Folder 115)
    Woman thumbs her nose at the Jew.
  - Jewish Scottsman "Say, Kid! If That Aint Camouflage, Ask Me What Is!", 1918 ca. (Box 13, Folder 116)
    Caricature of a Scottish Jew
  - Painted Jewish Caricatures: Jews Are Scratching Their Fleas, 1915 ca. (Box 13, Folder 117)
  - Levy With A Gun, 1910 ca. (Box 13, Folder 118)
    "Levy's Publicity Stunt. A vulgar guest perfromance brought rich returns, but in the long run was too dangerous."
  - Humorous Jewish Caricatures Jewish Merchants Consult, 1908 ca. (Box 13, Folder 119)
  - Lodz Ghetto currency, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 127)
    Two "50 Pfennig" and two "Eine Mark" notes bearing the reproduced signature of "Der Aelteste der Juden in Litzmannstadt M. Rumkowski"
  - Yellow Star of David Badge, 1939-1945; Series 2 (Box 13, Folder 128)
    Gift of Jan J. Simko, 01/25/2010 (2010.004)
    Found among possessions of Ms. Viola Paul, Vineland, N.J. A Jewish immigrant from Czechoslovakia, she was born in Sucany, a small town in the north of Slovakia and was probably in her late forties during WWII. Donated by Dr. Jan Simko, whose mother's brother was married to Ms. Paul.
    No information identifying the owner of the Star of David exists.
  - Lodz Ghetto currency, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    One "Zwei Mark" and one "Fuenf Mark" note bearing the reproduced signature of "Der Aelteste der Juden in Litzmannstadt M. Rumkowski"
  - Directory of Jewish Refugees form (probably from Shanghai), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    Written in both English and Chinese or Japanese, this form records personal and immigration information pertaining to Charlotte Gruenberg, a Jewish dressmaker whose passport was issued in Vienna. A photograph is adhered to the form.
  - German Newspapers, 1933-1934 (Map-folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Artifacts, 1916-1953
  Scope and Contents
  While the other artifacts in this collection relate to the Holocaust or the Nazi era, and thus are assigned to Series 2: Anti-Semitica, Series 3: Miscellaneous Artifacts consists of items documenting other facets of Jewish life in America and Europe.
  - Ticket for High Holiday synagogue seat, 1953 (Box 16, Folder 132)
    Services held at Chevre Ets Heym Mahzike ha-Ra, 24 Snediker Avenue, Brooklyn, New York. The ticket lists Cantor Yoseph Narflus, Synagogue President Chaim Koppel Glik, and Vice President Ben-Zion Piken.
    Ticket found in I. Edward Kiev Judaica Collection book donated by Walter Kurt Kahn, Professor Emeritus of Engineering and Applied Science at the George Washington University.
  - Postcard of Traunstein von Ettendorf, Germany, April 27, 1916 (Box 16, Folder 133)
    Postcard addressed to Fräulein Erna (illegible surname) in Wiesbaden. The handwritten message is very difficult to read but appears to include "greetings and kisses" from the recipient's brother, whose signature is illegible.
    Postcard found in I. Edward Kiev Judaica Collection book (BM 675 .F45 A3 1864 v. 1) donated by Walter Kurt Kahn, Professor Emeritus of Engineering and Applied Science at the George Washington University.